Guide to the Pratt Institute collection 1985.056
Brooklyn Historical Society
Pratt Institute collection
1888-2015
Brooklyn Historical Society
1985.056
4 Linear Feet in two record cartons, five manuscript boxes, three oversize folders and one flat file folder.
The Pratt Insitute collection contains printed items and ephemera produced by Pratt Institute and affiliated organizations. Pratt Institute was founded in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Clinton Hill in 1887 by wealthy oil merchant and philanthropist Charles Pratt.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired in 1985, donor unknown. The 1894 sewing course book was purchased for Brooklyn Historical Society by David Kahn in 1990.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into series and sub-series by type or by organization within or associated with Pratt Institute. Within series and sub-series, materials are arranged chronologically. Some items are housed out of chronological order due to size.
Historical Note
Pratt Institute was founded in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Clinton Hill in 1887 by wealthy oil merchant and philanthropist Charles Pratt. Originally from New England, Pratt moved to New York in early adulthood and later established his own successful oil business, Charles Pratt and Company, in 1867. He soon expanded his interests and acquired the Astral Oil Works refinery in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Williamsburg. In 1874, Pratt partnered with John D. Rockefeller, head of Standard Oil, and became co-owner of a consortium of petroleum refineries along the Brooklyn waterfront. Though he was highly successful, Pratt always lamented his limited amount of formal education, and established Pratt Insititute in order to provide young people with hands-on educational opportunities in industrial trades and engineering. Likely modeled after Cooper Union, the school founded in Manhattan by businessman and inventor Peter Cooper in 1859, Pratt Institute granted admission to both men and women regardless of race, and supplemented its core curriculum with courses in science and art. It also featured Brooklyn's first free library, aptly named the Pratt Institute Free Library, which served both students and faculty at Pratt as well as the general public. Since its founding, Pratt has achieved national recognition as one of New York City's distinguished educational institutions, and its main building and library were landmarked in 1981. As of 2023, Pratt functions as a private arts college, having discontinued its industrial and engineering programs in 1993. Pratt offers courses at its original Brooklyn campus as well as its satellite campuses in Manhattan and Utica in Central New York, and grants undergraduate and graduate degrees in architecture, art and design, the liberal arts, and library and information science.
Sources:
Grenier, Ellen M. Snyder, and Brooklyn Historical Society. Brooklyn!: An Illustrated History. Philadelphia: Temple University Press, 1996.
Pratt Institute. "Academics." Accessed November 3, 2010. http://www.pratt.edu/academics/.
Tabor, Mary B. "Pratt Decides to End School for Engineers." New York Times, December 13, 1991. Accessed November 3, 2010. http://www.nytimes.com/1991/12/13/nyregion/pratt-decides-to-end-school-for-engineers.html.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Related Materials
Brooklyn schools collection (CBHM.0006)
Ronald Shiffman collection on the Pratt Center for Community Development (2013.023)
Brooklyn yearbook collection (BCMS.0031)
Early Brooklyn libraries collection (ARC.168)
Scope and Contents
The Pratt Institute collection spans the period 1888 to 2015 and contains printed items and ephemera produced by Pratt Institute and affiliated organizations. The collection has been arranged into four series:
Series 1: Publications (which also contains Sub-Series 1.1: Catalogs and Sub-Series 1.2: Yearbooks),
Series 2: Ephemera,
Series 3: Library and Library School, with Sub-Series for the Free Library, Library, and School of Library Science, and
Series 4: Pratt Area Community Council (PACC).
Annual reports; Alumnae and alumni; Art schools -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Bulletins; Catalogs; Clinton Hill (New York, N.Y.); College students -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Education, Higher -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Education, Humanistic -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Engineering schools -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Handbooks; Libraries -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Library administration -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Library schools -- New York (State) -- Kings County -- Administration; Library schools -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Newsletters; Printed ephemera; Professional education -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Programs (documents); Publications; Reports; Speeches; Technical institutes -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Universities and colleges -- Alumni and alumnae -- New York (State) -- Kings County -- Societies, etc.; Universities and colleges -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Universities and colleges -- New York (State) -- Kings County -- Administration; Universities and colleges -- New York (State) -- Kings County -- Faculty; Urban renewal -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Yearbooks; New York (N.Y.). Committee on Slum Clearance; Pratt Institute. Free Library
- Series 1: Publications, 1888-2015
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes publications such as newsletters, bulletins, and magazines covering a wide variety of administrative, educational, and community issues. Also included are issues of the Pratt Institute Record and Pratt Institute Monthly containing annual reports from Pratt's various offices and departments for the period 1889 to 1905.
  - Pratt Institute Record, 1889-1892, 1903-1905 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Circular of Information, 1890-1891 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Art and Industrial Education, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    "Cooperative educational work by Pratt Institute and Prang Educational Company. The attention of teachers is respectfully invited to a cooperative undertaking...for the promotion of Art and Industrial education in public schools. The enclosed circular...outlines the general features."
  - Pratt Institute Monthly, 1892-1904 (Box 1, Folder 5-19)
  - Pratt Institute Monthly Index, 1894-1895, 1899-1900 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - How to Spell 100 Common Words, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    By M.L. Miner, Pratt Institute instructor.
  - Students' Bulletin, 1904 March 4 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Alumni fund reports, 1936-1937, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - The Story of Pratt Institute, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - News releases and clippings, 1948-1975, 1981, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Pratt Institute Bulletin - World Politics Program, 1955 (Box OS-34)
  - Asterisk, 1958 Spring (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Pratt Alumnus, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Pratt Alumnus, 1961-1973 (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
    There are no issues from 1971.
  - Pratt Institute Quarterly News, 1963-1969 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Pratt Planning Papers, 1963-1964 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    A publication of the Planning Department, School of Architecture. The 1964 issue consists of the proceedings of the Pratt Planning Conference, held May 14, 1964.
  - The Pratt Story, circa 1965 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    Describes the Pratt Program for the Decade Ahead and "details the areas where Pratt is planning growth and innovation."
  - Community Information Bulletin, 1967-1972, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Published by the Pratt Center for Community Improvement, later the Pratt Center for Community and Environmental Development.
  - Pratt Cannon, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Special Report, circa 1971 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Pratt Institute Bulletin, 1971 Fall (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Pratt Alumni Report, 1972 (Folder Flat File)
  - Pratt Is, 1972-1973 (Box OS-24)
  - Pratt Reports, 1975-1978 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Prattler, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Prism, 1971-1974 (Box OS-24)
  - Street, 1971-1976 (Box 2, Folder 12-14)
  - Street, Special Activities Edition, circa 1976 (Box OS-34)
  - Annual reports, 1975-1976, 1979-1980 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Prattfolio, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Prattfolio, 1998, 2014-2015 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Sub-series 1.1: Catalogs, 1888-1999
    This sub-series contains comprehensive Pratt Institute catalogs for the period 1888 to 1904, and a small number of course catalogs and bulletins for individual departments and programs spanning the period 1892 to 1999.
    - 1888, 1890-1895 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - 1895-1898 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - 1903-1904 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - 1994 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Department of Domestic Science, 1892-1893 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - School of Fine and Applied Arts, 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Summer sessions, 1965, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 18, Folder Flat File)
    - School of Art and Design Creative Arts Therapy, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - School of Continuing Education, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - School of Professional Studies, 1991, 1994, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Sub-series 1.2: Yearbooks, 1918-1970
    - Annual, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Prattonia, 1936, 1942, 1963, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 20-23)
- Series 2: Ephemera, 1889-circa 1980s
  This series contains programs pertaining to various events at Pratt Institute, including commencements, inaugurations, and exhibitions occurring intermittently throughout the period 1898 to 2004; one promotional booklet from 1966; and pamphlets containing speeches delivered by various presidents of Pratt Institute from 1959 to 1970. Also included are a pamphlet on the Pratt Institute Neighborhood Association, a student charitable organization, circa 1900; and pamphlets on the Thrift Savings, Loan and Building Fund, a program established by Charles Pratt to assist students with financial and housing issues, dating from 1889 to 1915. Other miscellaneous items are included in the series.
  - The Thrift, 1889-1903 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Historical note
    "The Thrift was founded October 2d, 1889, by Charles Pratt, to promote habits of thrift...The Thrift is organized and designed to aid in the work carried on at Pratt Institute, but is not conducted by the Institute, nor is the Institute responsible for it."
    The Thrift began as the Pratt Institue Thrift Association and eventually had the name The Thrift Savings, Loan, and Building Fund.
  - Exhibitions, circa 1890s, circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Sewing course book, 1894; M1990.060 (Box 6)
    A scrapbook of sewing models and instructions with handwritten title: "Children's Course / Sewing / Models with Instruction / used by / Pratt Institute / Brooklyn, New York / Department of Domestic Art / 1894."
  - Department of Kindergartens application, circa early 19th century (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Pratt Institute Neighborship Association, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Events, 1905-2004 (Box 2, Folder 28, Folder Flat File)
    Includes programs, flyers, or postcards for Pratt Institute High School Class Day Exercises (1905), 1958 commencement, lectures, symposia, Founder's Day, and a 1972 student protest.
  - Poster, circa 1980s (Box OS-34)
- Series 3: Library and Library School, 1894-circa 2000
  - Sub-series 3.1: Pratt Institute Free Library, 1894-1940
    This series contains published annual reports of the Pratt Institute Free Library for the periods 1897 to 1913 and 1922 to 1940. Beginning in 1923, the publications also include the annual reports of the Pratt Institute School of Library Science. Additional items in this series include library booklists and bulletins for the period 1894 to 1940.
    - Bulletin, 1894, 1895, 1899, 1900 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Reports, 1897-1940 (Box 3, Folder 1-6)
    - Mary W. Plummer letter, circa early 1900s (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Includes information on library staff salaries.
    - Library directory, circa early 1900s (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Bookplate, circa early 19th century (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Monthly Bulletin, 1905-1912 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    - Books on Electricity list, 1906 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Technical Books, 1908-1925 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Quarterly Booklists, 1912-1923 (Box 4, Folder 3-5)
    - Quarterly Booklists, 1923-1940 (Box 5, Folder 1-5)
  - Sub-series 3.2: Pratt Institute Library, 1940-1996
    - Quarterly Booklist, 1940-1943 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Report, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Ephemera, 1983, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Sub-series 3.3: School of Library Science, 1912-1990
    - School of Library Science handbook, 1912, 1914-1919 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - The P-Slip, 1966 June (Box 6, Folder 6)
      "A very occasional publication of the Pratt Institute Graduate Library School Alumni Association."
    - Bulletin, 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - GSLIS Alumni Association newsletter, 1972-1973 Winter (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Ephemera, 1972-circa 2000 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      Catalogs, programs, and news releases relating to Pratt's Graduate School of Library and Information Science (GSLIS), later the School of Information and Library Science (SILS).
    - Catalogue, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Pratt Perspectives / GSLIS Perspectives, 1974-1976 (Box 6, Folder 6, Folder Flat File)
      Published by the Graduate School of Library and Information Science (GSLIS).
    - News & Notes from Graduate Library and Information Science Program, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Series 4: Pratt Area Community Council (PACC), 1953-2003
  Now known as IMPACCT Brooklyn, the Pratt Area Community Council is a community development corporation serving the neighborhoods of Fort Greene, Clinton Hill, Bedford Stuyvesant, Crown Heights, and Prospect Heights.
  - Slum Clearance Plan Under Title I of the Housing Act of 1949: Pratt Institute Area, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Pratt Area Community Bulletin, 1974-1977 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - PACC Awards Dinner Dance program, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Newsletter, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Fundraising letter, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 9)